Guide to the Roman Brackman Papers MC.297
New York University Archives
Roman Brackman Papers
1940-2012
1968-2005
New York University Archives
Brackman, Roman, 1931-
MC.297
6.05 linear feet in 14 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box.
Roman Brackman (1931- ) is a native of Moscow, Russia. In 1949 Brackman unsuccessfully attempted to escape from the Soviet Union and was sentenced to 10 years in the Norilsk Gulag penal labor camp. While there, he participated in a Norilsk prisoner uprising in the summer of 1953. He has written multiple works, including The Secret File of Joseph Stalin: A Hidden Life. The Roman Brackman Papers consist of materials created and collected by Brackman in the course of his research and writing related to various topics concerning Joseph Stalin and the history, politics, and economics of the Soviet Union and Russia. Materials include newspaper and magazine clippings in both English and Russian; articles written by Brackman; and correspondence. Publicity and reviews related to his book The Secret File of Joseph Stalin: A Hidden Life can also be found in this collection. The collection also contains subject files and correspondence related to other areas of interest to Brackman, including the political career of Richard M. Nixon, the Watergate scandal, and Republican Party activities in the late 20th century.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Roman Brackman in August 2018; the accession number associated with this gift is 2018.032.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Roman Brackman (1931- ) is a native of Moscow, Russia. In 1949 Brackman unsuccessfully attempted to escape from the Soviet Union and was sentenced to 10 years in the Norilsk Gulag penal labor camp. While there, he participated in a Norilsk prisoner uprising in the summer of 1953. After being released in 1955, Brackman left the Soviet Union and emigrated to the United States in 1962. He graduated from City College of New York (B.A., 1965) and earned his doctorate in history from New York University in 1980. Brackman has written multiple works, including The Secret File of Joseph Stalin: A Hidden Life.
Source: Brackman, Roman. From Hell to Paradise. CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform, 2012.
Scope and Contents
The Roman Brackman Papers consist of materials created and collected by Brackman in the course of his research and writing related to various topics concerning Joseph Stalin and the history, politics, and economics of the Soviet Union and Russia. Brackman's subject files often contain newspaper and magazine clippings in both English and Russian; photographs; research notes; and correspondence. Publicity, correspondence, and reviews related to Brackman's book The Secret File of Joseph Stalin: A Hidden Life, can also be found in this collection. The collection also contains subject files and correspondence related to other areas of interest, including the political career of Richard M. Nixon, the Watergate scandal, Jimmy Carter, and Republican Party activities in the late 20th century.
Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936.; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1936-1953; History -- Study and teaching -- Russia; Soviet Union -- Historiography; Clippings (information artifacts); Research notes.; Correspondence.; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974; Brackman, Roman, 1931-; Stalin, Joseph, 1879-1953.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-
- Stalin -- Russian Articles, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Okhrana Appendix, 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Stalin -- Images, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Routledge -- Stalin, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Stalin -- Psychicly Sick, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Stalin, Lev, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Syrkin, Norman, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Alexksinsky, Grigory -- Oxpaha, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Stalin, Joseph, 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gromyko, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Harting, Arkady -- Oxpaha, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Berdiaev, Nikolay, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Vasiliev, I.P. -- Oxpaha, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Katyn, 1940, 1976-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Lyushkov, Genrickh, 1968-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Lee, Russel, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Dzerzhinsky, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Прobokatopbl, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Narcissism, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Yakir, P., 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Nechaev, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Archives, 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Stalin, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Vesselago, N., 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Rosenberg, 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Rapport, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Litvinov, Maxim, 1957, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Masaryk, 1968, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Raskolnikov, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Redlich, Shimon, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Orlov, Alexander, 1956, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Okhrana, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Ryumin, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Ehrenburg, Ilya, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Doskoevsky, F., undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Doctors' Plot, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Freud, S., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Goloschchekin, She -- Oxpaha, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Bulhanin, N. A., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Stalin, Yakov, 1968, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Eremin, A -- Oxpaha, 1974-1992 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Stalin -- Jews, 1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Wallenberg, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Vasiliev, A.T., undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Timashuk, Lidiva, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Meyerhold, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Mikhoels, Solomon, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Kolpashevo, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Rutin, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Lizarov, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Ivan the Terrible, 1956-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Sharia, N., undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Volkogona, 1988-1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Tуxaчebckoгo, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Svetlov, Felix, 1975-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Sneh, Moshe, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Stalin -- Vasily, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Selman, Abrasha, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Dolgun, A., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Nixon, 1974-2001 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Hiss, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Nixon, 1973-1977, 1994, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
- Selected Articles, 1972-1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Nixon Letter to Editor, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Badash, 1986-1998 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Hiss (Nixon), 1975-2006 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Deep Throat, 2003-2007 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Deep Throat -- Chase, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Dean, John, 2000-2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Okhrana Archives, 1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Stalin Children, 1981-1996 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Stalin -- Movie, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Stalin -- Okhrana, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1965-1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Serebriakova, Anna, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Golovechev, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Stalin, 1992-2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Bagratuni, R. -- Oxpaha, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Crimea and Soviet Jews, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- The Secret Life of Stalin, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Lee, Eric, 1992, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Mor, R., 1990 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Stalin, Joseph -- Mental Health, 1973-1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Bolscheviki, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Portraits, 2003, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Krasny Arkhiv, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Katanova, L., 1977, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Kaminsky -- Detstvo, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Ilizarov, 1967, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Jews, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Glantz, David, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Levine, Don, 1956-1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Berger-Barzilai, J., 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- G. Kennan, 1968-2001 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Barzilay, I., 1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Guriel, Boris, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Mikunis, S., 1969 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Beni Marshek, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Palestina, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Lifshitz, David, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Ternopoler, 1969, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Evseev Sheet, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Rosenbergs, 1975, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Stalin, Joseph, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Stalin-Hitler Secret Protocol, 1989, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Articles, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Yvette -- Norylsk, 2003-2006 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Yvette, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Heifets, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Beria, 1967-1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Cletlov Felix, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Nepoptobcka, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Prison Camp Songs, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Lev Netto, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Vilia Svechinsky, 1972-1998 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Brackman, R. -- Articles, 1972-1985, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Norilsk Uprising, 1991-2003 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Interviews -- Israel Copies, 1969-2009 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- My Articles, 1968-2001 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Osyck, 1993, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- протокоja, 1990, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
- My Articles, 1973-2009 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Reviews of My Stalin Book, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Carter -- Atomic Bomb, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Watergate, 2012 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Dean, 1973-1999 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
- Israel -- Carter, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Carter, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Hadrian, Emperor, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Hillary Clinton and Bob Herbert, 2000-2008 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Carter, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Reactional Formations, Carter -- Merlish, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Carter, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Carter Family, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Sakharov, 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Smith, Edward Ellis, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Not Meaning Carter, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Carter, 1980-2009 (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
- Egypt Israel -- Carter, 1977-1980 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Obama, 2007-2009 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Carter -- Iran -- Huyser, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Carter, 1976-1985 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Carter, 1980-1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Carter, Jimmy, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Rosalynn Carter, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Innovations Carter, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- God Complex, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Iran -- General, 1978-1980 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Blacks, Jews, Young -- Carter, 1979-1980 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Lipchitz, Jacques, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Iran -- Rescue, Carter Mission, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Moral Blindness -- Carter, 1976-1978 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Powell, Colin, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Reagan, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Abkin, Davia, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Vietnam, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Stalin, 1967, 2001-2002 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Georgia, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Primakov, 1991-2004 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Putin, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Svechinsky, 1973-1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Watergate, 1968-1977 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Deep Throat, 1975-2008 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Kalik, M., 1971-1977 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Israel, Chechnya, 2001-2002 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Slepak, V., 1977 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Svetlov, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Israel, 2001-2002 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Thomas Friedman, 2001-2007 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Louis, Victor, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Letters -- Israel, 1968-1973 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- General Thomas Kelly, 1991, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Obama, 2007-2008 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Arafat -- Clinton, 1980-2004 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Moran -- Kennedy, 2003-2005 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Blavatnik, 2005-2008 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Soros, 2003-2007 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Mama, 1974-1978 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Litvinov, Pavel, 1968-1975 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Bremner, Herbert, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Chalidze, Valery N., 1972-1973 (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Dean, John, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- My Letters, 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Truman, Harry, 1970-1973 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Vilia -- Misha, 1974-1986 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Vilia -- Garik, 1977, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Vilia, 1996-2006 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Putin, 2003-2007 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Gordon Liddy, 2000-2002 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Dean, 1975-2005 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- John Dean Article, 1974-1976 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Woodward, 1975-2006 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Sam Vaknin, circa 2008 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Watergate, 1973-2007 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Couusu, 1992-2002 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Foreign Policy, 1977-1980 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Carter, 1973-1980 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
- Brackman, Roman -- Articles, Copies, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Carter Staff, 1978-1980 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Dean, 1974-1980 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Bruce Herschensohn, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Clement Stone, Max Fisher, Rabbi Baruch Korff, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 11)
- Shula Behat, 2011 (Box 14, Folder 12)
- Goberman, M.A., 1974 (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Gordon, Mila, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
- Arnie Steinberg, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Pavel Goldstein, undated (Box 14, Folder 16)
- Palatnik, R., 1972, 2009 (Box 14, Folder 17)
- U.J.A., 1976 (Box 14, Folder 18)
- Articles, Books By Brackman Publicity, 1974-2008 (Box 14, Folder 19)
- Publicity, 1986-2008 (Box 14, Folder 20)
- Carter, 1978-1993 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Michael -- Golan Heights, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Letters, 2006-2007 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Ruth Wisse, 2007 (Box 15, Folder 4)